<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The royal law of God revived wherein you may see that all nations of men may keep in it a royal society ... / G.F.</title>
            <author>Fox, George, 1624-1691.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1672</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 109 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A40240</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F1892</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R28007</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">10325489</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 10325489</idno>
            <idno type="VID">44859</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A40240)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 44859)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1384:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The royal law of God revived wherein you may see that all nations of men may keep in it a royal society ... / G.F.</title>
                  <author>Fox, George, 1624-1691.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>44 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1671/2.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  Apologetic works.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:44859:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:44859:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Royal Law of GOD REVIVED: Wherein You may ſee, That all Nations of Men may keep in it a Royal Society; and by obeying the Principl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of God in them, which brings Men to do the Roya<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Law; and to do unto all men, as they would have al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> men to do unto them: which Royal Law of God an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers that of God in every Man and Woman in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> whole World, which they tranſgreſſing, are judged by the Royal Law of God, in doing that unto others, as they would not have others do unto them, and they to be without natural Affections; which Royal Law brings all men to have Natural Affections, and to do unto all men, as they would have them to do unto them.</p>
            <p>G. F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Jam. 2.8.</hi>
               </bibl> If ye fulfil the Royal Law, according to the Scripture, <hi>Thou ſhalt Love thy Neighbour as thy ſelf,</hi> ye do well.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>t. 7.12.</hi>
               </bibl> Whatſoever ye would that men ſhould do unto you, <hi>do ye even ſo to them.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>Printed in the Year, 1671/2</p>
         </div>
         <div type="epigraph">
            <pb facs="tcp:44859:2"/>
            <q>
               <p>Who they are that break this Royal Law of God.</p>
               <p>Them that Quench, Vex and grieve the good Spirit of God; and hate the Light of Chriſt; and walk deſpightfully againſt the Spirit of Grace; and make Shipwrack of Faith, and of a good Conſcience.</p>
               <p>And alſo, They are them that keep the Royal Law of God, that walk in the Spirit of God, and in Faith, and a good Conſcience; and love the Light, Chriſt, who inlightens every man that comes into the World.</p>
            </q>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:44859:2"/>
            <head>The Royal Law of God Revived, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>ALL People upon the Face of the whole Earth, both High and Low, Rich and Poor, know that (as the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Acts</hi> 15.26.) <hi>God hath made of one Blood all Nations of Men, for to dwell on all the Face of the Earth.</hi> So all Men and Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men are of God's making, his Workmanſhip, and the Works of his Hands and Creation; and he it is that gives Life and Breath unto all: <hi>And hath determined the Times before appointed, and the Bounds of their Habitations,</hi> ſaith he.</p>
            <p>And ſaith <hi>Moſes, Deut.</hi> 32.8. <hi>The Moſt High divided to the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions their Inheritance, when he ſeparated the Sons of</hi> Adam, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> acknowledgeth, <hi>Pſa.</hi> 24.1. <hi>The Earth is the Lord's, and the fulneſs thereof; the World, and they that dwell there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in; which he hath diſtributed unto the Sons of Men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And the Lord is called, <hi>The God of the Spirits of all Fleſh, Num.</hi> 27.16. And ſo ſaith likewiſe the Apoſtle, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.6. <hi>One God and Father of all, who is above all, through all, and in you all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now ſeeing the Lord hath made all Nations of Men and Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men upon the Earth of one Blood and Mould, to dwell upon the Face of the Earth; and that the Earth is the Lord's, and the Fulneſs thereof; and he gives the encreaſe, and hath diſtributed unto the Sons and Daughters of <hi>Adam;</hi> What then is the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that makes a Diſcord amongſt all the Sons and Daughters of men, but the Devil (the Cauſe of all Diſcord) who is out of Truth, and ſo leads them out of Unity with God, and with one another; ſo that they cannot Commerce, Trade, and hold a Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondence &amp; a Concord in Civil things of the Creation of the Earth: ſeeing the Earth is the Lord's, and the Fulneſs thereof: that all Nations of Men cannot hold a Commerce, Unity and Concord (I ſay) in theſe outward things, though they cannot agree in and about Matters of Religion and Worſhip, and abou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> their Teachings and Wayes? What is the matter now, that they do not agree; ſeeing there is no Diſcord nor Diſagreement in
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:44859:3"/>the Way of the Lord, which is Chriſt Jeſus, the Heavenly Man, who is the Way to God the Father: Neither is there any Diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement in the Fellowſhip of the Spirit, nor in the Worſhip, nor in the Spirit, nor in the Truth. And therefore are not all the Diſagreements and Diſcords throughout all the World about Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligions, Worſhips and Doctrines; about, I ſay, ſuch as men have made, which are called National Worſhips, National Wayes, and National Religions, that are all the Works of Mens hands? And there are ſuch a Multitude of them in all the Nations of the <hi>World,</hi> which hinders them from Civil Commerce, Civil Society of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Affections, that ought to be amongſt Mankind: For where theſe Natural Affections, or Affections of Nature are not, they will deſtroy one another about their Religions, Worſhips and Ways: and certainly ſuch doings are not of God, nor of Chriſt, who ſaid to his Diſciples, when they would have had Fire to come down from Heaven, to conſume them that would not receive him, <hi>That they did not know what ſpirit they were of.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore do all people that Perſecute others for not receiving their Doctrines, their Worſhips, their Wayes, and Religions; yea; perſecuting for not receiving of Chriſt; they know not what Spirit they are of.</p>
            <p>Now mark the tender Nature of Chriſt, <hi>Who,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>came not to deſtroy mens lives, but to ſave them.</hi> Therefore they that would have mens lives taken away for Religion or not receiving of Chriſt, They have not the Affections of Nature. 2d, They do not know what ſpirit they are of themſelves. 3d, They have not the Mind of Chriſt. 4th, No man will truſt his Body, Soul or Spirit in the hands of ſuch, that do not know what ſpirit they are of themſelves.</p>
            <p>Have any of all theſe, that make Religions, VVayes and Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips, and Doctrines of their own, any Affections to Nature, who will deſtroy people becauſe they will not conform to that Religion, VVay and VVorſhip that they have ſet up. As now look over all the whole VVorld, and all the Religions therein, and ſee and conſider, Who they are that have deſtroyed, burnt, and put to death ſuch as would not conform to the Religion, and VVay and VVorſhip, that they have made: And have not theſe firſt been Truce-Brea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap> to and with God, and then with Man,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:44859:3"/>and fallen from that Religion that is from above, and from his Religion, his VVorſhip, and Truth, his VVay Chriſt Jeſus; and then the Devil entred them, who hath led them to deſtroy one another about their Religions, VVayes, and their VVorſhips which they have ſet up, and were not ſet up by the Lord, but forbidden by Chriſt (and ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>He is not worſhipped with the Worſhips of Mens Hands, Acts</hi> 17.24.) who is Lord over all, and would have all Repent, and feel after him; and ſo to Repent as to change from their Worſhips, and the Works of their own hands, the Religions, the Worſhips, and Wayes that they have made; and come to God by Chriſt Jeſus, who is the VVay to God; and ſo through him receive that Religion that is from above; and ſo to worſhip God in the Spirit and in the Truth.</p>
            <p>And is there any Religion to be owned, or any VVorſhip, from ſuch which are without Natural Affections? And is it not the Devil that makes Religions, VVayes and VVorſhips, and leads them to be ſo peeviſh about them, and in a blind Zeal to contend ſo earneſtly for them; which brings them from a civil Commerce, and makes them uncapable of a civil Society, and a Correſpondency amongſt Mankind: And that ſpirit that hath led them to make Religion, VVorſhips and VVayes, and to fall out when they have done, that Spirit hath deſtroyed the civil So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety, the civil Commerce amongſt Mankind almoſt over all the whole VVorld; that when they come into civil things, a civil Commerce, that tends to a civil Society in Natural things, they fall out about the ſeveral natural VVorſhips, Religions and VVayes, which they have made, by which a peeviſh and perverſe ſpirit ariſes in a blind Zeal for the VVorks of their own Hands, ſo as that they forget their Natural Affections, and fall upon de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying one another about Religions; and ſo break all civil So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety and Commerce amongſt men; which if there were but Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Affections, it would carry them above that peeviſh and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe ſpirit, that draws them after their own Handy-works; whereas, I ſay, if Natural Affections were but ſet over that, it would keep and preſerve the Bond of a civil Commerce, and civil Society with Mankind over the whole Univerſe.</p>
            <p>O! How ſhort is all Mankind, both <hi>Chriſtians, Jews, Turks,</hi> and all the reſt, of that Royal Law, which is, <hi>To do to all Men
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:44859:4"/>as they would have them do unto them?</hi> If this Royal Law were duely kept, the true weight would be ſet up amongſt all Mankind in the whole world; and the true Meaſure, to meaſure every man, and to weigh every man, and to weigh himſelf, and to meaſure him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and to meaſure others; and to do nothing to any Man or Woman, but as they would have them do to them: This would keep up a Society in the whole World, that ſo Men might Trade. Commerce, and hold Correſpondence one with another amongſt all the Nations of men. And this is the Royal Law, in which all Mankind have their Liberty, <hi>For all to do to others, as they would have others do unto them:</hi> And here is Religion, which is above all religions that they have made with their hands; and this will keep down that perverſe ſpirit in all Mankind in the whole world, if they keep and obey the Royal Law, which is, <hi>To do to all Men, as they would have them do to them;</hi> then all Mankind would have their Liberty in this; and in this no man will over-reach, couzen, defraud nor oppreſs in any Bargain and Merchandize whatſoever; for if he would not that they ſhould do ſo to him, then ſurely he will not do ſo to them.</p>
            <p>So here then is Juſtice ſet up, and the Line of Righteouſneſs, and the Plummet; and every Nation, Country and Iſland might ſerve one another in this Royal and Juſt Law; doing unto them as they would have others do to them, in all things that are civil; that one Neighbour-country hath not, or another Country is deſtitute of, to ſerve one another with thoſe things that are civil, and natural, and outward: <hi>For the Earth is the Lord's, and the Fulneſs thereof, who gives the increaſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And all Nations of men are to uſe, and order, and diſpoſe of theſe earthly things, and the Fulneſs of the Earth, where the Lord hath given the Increaſe, with his Royal Law, one Nation to another, one Country to another; which Royal Law is to do to another, as they would have them do to them; and ſo one Country to another, one Nation to another Nation, to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed by this Royal Law of God, which is above all other Laws of mens making, which is, I ſay, To do to others, as they would have others do unto them: And in this Equity, Truth, Juſtice and Honeſty is ſet up by this Royal Law of God, amongſt all the Countries, Tongues, and People, and Nations of men in the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:44859:4"/>whole World, and preſerving civil Society, and right Manners; for if no man would have any corrupt Communication ſpoken unto him, then he muſt give none to any other; or if a man would not have another to oppreſs or exact on him, he not doing ſo to any other, thereby the Royal Law in ſo doing is kept; or if he would not have any man to abuſe, kill, or wound him, he not doing ſo to another, here the Royal Law is kept.</p>
            <p>And thus one Neighbour-town ſerves another with ſuch things that that Town has not; and the other ſerves them likewiſe with ſuch things that they want: and one Country ſerves another with the things that another hath not, and that ſerves the other again with the things that they have not: So one Nation ſerves another with the things that they have not, and they ſerve them again with the things that they have not; and ſo all Nations to ſerve one another with the things that the Lord hath given them: <hi>For the Earth,</hi> in the firſt place, <hi>is the Lord's, and the Ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs thereof; and he gives the increaſe, and hath diſtributed theſe things unto the Nations of Men, whom he hath made of one Blood and Mould to dwell upon the Face of the Earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that theſe Towns, Countries and Nations, by this Royal Law of Liberty (by and with which Law, they have Liberty to ſerve one another in Equity, Truth and Juſtice) they may have and preſerve a true <hi>Commerce,</hi> a true <hi>Correſpondency,</hi> a true <hi>Society</hi> in all Towns, Countries and Nations in the whole Univerſe of Mankind one with another, whereby, and in which they will honour the Lord, and be preſerved in all Towns, Countries and Nations, I ſay, as men, by this Royal Law, and will have their Liberty in and by this Royal Law.</p>
            <p>Object. But if you object and ſay, <hi>That all men in all Towns, Countries and Nations have nothing of God in them to anſwer this Royal Law of God, and to keep it; and conſequently to preſerve this Society amongſt all Countries Towns and Nations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> They have ſomething of God in them to anſwer that Royal Law of God: For God, who gave forth that Royal Law, he is the God of the Spirits of all Fleſh, by which Spirit they may anſwer his Law; and God will judge the World in Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, according to the Secrets of every ones Heart, by the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Man Chriſt Jeſus, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.16. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.24, 25. Whereby is
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:44859:5"/>ſignified, that there is ſomething, that is ſecret, of him in them. <hi>God</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>ſhall judge in that day the Secrets of Men by Jeſus Chriſt, according to my Goſpel, which Goſpel is the Power of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now if God judgeth the world of Men according to the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, that is, according to the inviſible Power of God; it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>notes that there is ſomething inviſible of God in man; elſe, how can the inviſible God judge the World in Righteouſneſs, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his inviſible Power, which is the Goſpel, which this inviſible Power in man doth anſwer the Royal Law of God. And as Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Mat,</hi> 13.19, &amp;c. The Word is ſown upon all Grounds; and his Word is the Seed of God, which is Divine and Inviſible; to wit, The <hi>Stony, High-way, Thorny,</hi> and the <hi>Good Ground;</hi> ſo that no man is exempted, but all are left without Excuſe. And as he ſaith, ſpeaking of the Tallents, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.15, &amp;c. <hi>That to every man is given a Meaſure, according to his Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity;</hi> yea, to the very ſloathful Servant that hid it: So now, if every man hath a Meaſure according to his Ability, it is but juſt for him to give an Account thereof according to his Meaſure, that anſwers the Lord, who hath given him his Meaſure accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his Ability; therein is his Judgment Juſt, and God is Righteous in his Judgments, who rewards every man according to his Works and his Words, for which he muſt give account, and according to his Doings, <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.36.</p>
            <p>So then it may clearly be ſeen here, that there is ſomething of God in man, to anſwer his Royal Laws, to keep a Society in it. And as the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.19, 20. concerning the <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then Gentiles,</hi> That <hi>that which might be known of God is manifeſt in them; for God hath ſhewed it unto them:</hi> And further, ſaith he, <hi>For the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible things from the Creation of the World are clearly ſeen, &amp;c.</hi> that is to ſay, His Eternal-Power and Godhead are ſeen, foraſmuch as they are underſtood by the works of the Creation of the World; ſo that they are left without Excuſe, <hi>becauſe, when they knew God, they glorified him not as God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now mark, Here you ſee 'tis plain, that here was ſomething of God in the <hi>Heathens,</hi> by which they knew God, which God hath manifeſted to them, by which they might anſwer the Royal Law of God: But when they went from this of God in them, and glorified him not as God, then they ſet up their own Worſhips
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:44859:5"/>and Wayes, and loſt the courſe of Nature, and did things againſt Nature: ſo here they forſook the Lord, and his Wayes, and Religion; and then perſecuted others, that would not follow them, and their Wayes and Worſhips; and ſo break the Royal Society which is in the Royal Law, going from that of God in them, which ſhould anſwer it: and then you may ſee downwards in the ſame Chapter what they worſhipped, and what they follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and how they brought the Wrath of God upon them; and how they held the Truth in Unrighteouſneſs, which was filled with all manner of evil; which men, though they knew that the Judgment of God was upon ſuch as commit ſuch things, yet they did not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard God, but were without natural Affections: So here when they erred from that of God in them, they loſt Natural Affections, Affections of Nature to them that were of the ſame Blood and Mould; and alſo, going from that of God in them, they went from the Royal Law of God, which ſhould have kept them in Natural Affections, and in a Royal Society by the Royal Law; and ſo there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by Indignation, and Wrath and Anguiſh came upon every ſoul of them that do Evil, of the <hi>Jew</hi> firſt, and alſo of the <hi>Gentiles;</hi> ſignifying thereby, that there is ſomething in the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> as well as in the <hi>Jews;</hi> to which, if they act contrary, they go from the Royal Law, and ſo bring the Judgments of God upon them, who Rewards every one according to his Works: For the <hi>Jews,</hi> that had the Law, the outward written Law, and the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> that had not the outward written Law, do by Nature the things contained in the written Law, which ſhows the deeds of the Law written in their hearts; ſo according to this the Lord ſhall judge the ſecrets of men by <hi>Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> according to the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>Now the <hi>Gentiles</hi> having the Law written in their Hearts, and do the deeds of the Law; the <hi>Jews</hi> having the outward written Law, and not doing the things contained in the written Law; the <hi>Gentiles</hi> were Judges over them; that is, <hi>The Gentiles were ſet over them.</hi> Now here its plain, that there was ſomething in the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> as alſo in the <hi>Jews,</hi> to anſwer the Royal Law of God, which ſhould bring them to do (if they would but obey it) to all men as they would have them do unto them, and to keep both the Natural Affections and Royal Society.</p>
            <p>For now, If they that are called <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> who have a written
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:44859:6"/>Goſpel, and are Tranſgreſſors of it, as the <hi>Jews,</hi> that had a written Law, and were not the Keepers and the Doers of it, whereby the <hi>Gentiles</hi> judged them that did not the things contained in the Law, having the Law written in their hearts, and were the Doers of it.</p>
            <p>So likewiſe now in our Ag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> as is ſaid before, All <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> that have a written Goſpel, and do not the things contained in it; theſe, whom they call <hi>Heathens,</hi> or <hi>Indians,</hi> or <hi>Turks,</hi> that do the things contained in the Goſpel, viz. <hi>The obeying of the Power and Spirit, which led them to do unto all men, as they would have them do unto them;</hi> theſe are Judges of the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> ſo called; who ſay, <hi>They have the Goſpel,</hi> and yet do it not, and do to others thoſe things that they would not have others do unto them; theſe, I ſay, are Breakers of the Royal Law: <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> in the firſt place, are judged before the <hi>Heathen;</hi> and as the <hi>Jews</hi> firſt, and then the <hi>Gentiles;</hi> ſo the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> firſt, and then the <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then:</hi> And ſo God is a Reſpecter of no mans Perſon, who judges the World in Righteouſneſs; but is a Rewarder accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to every ones Works, who walk not according to his Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Law of Liberty. And ſo its clear, that there is ſomething of God in all <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles, Chriſtians</hi> and <hi>Heathens,</hi> to bring them to anſwer that Royal Law, and to follow it, and not their own Imaginations; through which they may come to natural Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, and do unto all men, as thou wouldſt have them do un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee: So God, I ſay, is no Reſpecter of Perſons, who judges the World in Righteouſneſs.</p>
            <p>For the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>If the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncircumciſion, which by Nature keep the Law, judge the</hi> Jews, <hi>which being under the Letter of Circumciſion, and do tranſgreſs the Law.</hi> So I ſay, They that be under the Profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Letter of <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> and do tranſgreſs the Letter of <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> he that hath not the Letter as <hi>Chriſtian</hi> hath, and yet by Nature doth keep in the Law of <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> judgeth the <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians,</hi> and that that is ſet up in them: And therefore, as the Apoſtle ſaith; <hi>He is not a</hi> Jew, <hi>that is one outward;</hi> neither is he a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> that is one outward in Profeſſion, without Poſſeſſion; <hi>but he is a</hi> Jew <hi>that is one inward in the Spirit, and not in the Letter;</hi> and ſo he is a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> that is one inward, and not in the Letter, a Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Profeſſor; but one who is in the Heart, and in the Spirit of Chriſt Jeſus; though the outward Letter Profeſſor of <hi>Jew</hi> and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:44859:6"/>
               <hi>Chriſtian</hi> hath ſomething of God in him, which ſhould lead him to obey that which he doth profeſs, and to poſſeſs that which he doth profeſs; for that hath the Praiſe of God, and not of men.</p>
            <p>And in <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.9. ſaith the Apoſtle <hi>Paul, What better are the</hi> Jews <hi>then the</hi> Gentiles, ſpoken of before? <hi>they are in no wiſe better; for we have proved already, that both</hi> Jew <hi>and</hi> Gentile <hi>were all under ſin.</hi> So now, What difference is there between the Profeſſor of God, and of the Scriptures, and them that did not profeſs? So what difference is there between <hi>Chriſtians, that do profeſs,</hi> and thoſe that <hi>do not profeſs;</hi> ſeeing all are concluded under Sin, out of the Life, ſo as to Jew and Gentile there is no difference, out of Chriſt, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>converted? But now <hi>Jew</hi> and <hi>Gentile</hi> in Chriſt converted, <hi>Sythian</hi> and <hi>Barbarian</hi> are all one in <hi>Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> Gal. 3.28.</p>
            <p>Now though there be no difference between <hi>Jew</hi> and <hi>Gentile (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing concluded under Sin)</hi> in an unconverted Eſtate, nor no diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between <hi>Chriſtian</hi> and <hi>Heathen (concluded under Sin)</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>converted; yet nevertheleſs there is ſomething of God in them which they do diſobey, both in Jew and Gentile, Chriſtian and Heathen, which brings the Wrath of God upon them for their Diſobedience; which if they did obey that of God in them, both <hi>Jew</hi> and <hi>Gentile, Chriſtian</hi> and <hi>Heathen,</hi> it would bring them to the Royal Law of God, and to the Royal Society, and to the Natural Affections, and to keep their Word, and to do to all men as they would have them do to them; For certainly they would have no man break their Word with them, and therefore they muſt break their Word with no man; That is a juſt Law, <hi>Do unto all men as, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hear the words of Chriſt to his Diſciples, who is the Second <hi>Adam,</hi> the Heavenly man, <hi>Joh.</hi> 16.8, 9, 10, <hi>&amp;c. I tell you of a truth, it is expedient for you that I go away; for if I go not away the Comforter will not come unto you: but if I go, I will ſend him unto you; And this Comforter is the Spirit of Truth, the Holy Ghoſt; and this Holy Ghoſt will lead the Diſciples into all Truth, and ſhew them things to come. And he ſhall take of mine (ſaith he) and give it unto you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now mark, in the firſt place, <hi>He ſhall lead them into all Truth;</hi> namely, his Diſciples, the Learners of Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
            <p n="2">2dly, The ſame Comforter, which is the Spirit of Truth, ſhall reprove the World of ſin, which they live in; and of the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:44859:7"/>they live in, which is the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt Jeſus; and ſhall reprove the World of their judgment; for all the <hi>world</hi> have a judgment, which is not the Judgment of God, which they judge one another about, and by which they ſet up their Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Wayes of Worſhip, by which they judge others that will not conform to them; and judge the Prophets of the Lord, and ſpiritual Men, to be Mad-men, and Fools; and Chriſt, the Son and Light of God, to be a Blaſphemer, a Devil; and the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, as Babblers, Turbulent Fellows, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Now what ſpirit were they in that had this judgment? and with what ſpirit did they judge, who are reproved by the Spirit, namely, <hi>the Comforter, the Holy Ghoſt?</hi> So all the World that comes from ſin, their judgment, their righteouſneſs, they muſt turn at the Reproof of this Spirit, the Holy Ghoſt, which leads the Saints into all Truth.</p>
            <p>And by this Heavenly Mans Doctrine, Chriſt Jeſus, you may ſee here is ſomething of God in every man, which would lead them to the Royal Law of God, and to do it, and act by it, and to lead them to Affections that are above, and to have Natural Affections, Affections of Nature, and to receive the Royal Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety in the Royal Law; and not to deſtroy Men and Women, who are part of the Creation of God, and of his VVorkmanſhip, for they that do deſtroy them about Religion, and VVayes, and VVorſhips, that they have made themſelves, and ſet up (but not by the Command of God) they deſtroy part of God's <hi>Creation.</hi> and God's <hi>Creatures,</hi> and the <hi>Workmanſhip of his Hands;</hi> though they do profeſs God, yet they deſtroy Man, who is made in the ſimilitude of God, and in ſo doing they would deſtroy God, if they could: <hi>For,</hi> as it is ſaid, <hi>he that hates his Brother is a Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlayer;</hi> and ſo no Man-ſlayer, having not eternal Life abiding in him, he cannot ſet up Religions, Wayes, nor Worſhips by which God is honoured. And theſe Men-ſlayers break the <hi>Concord,</hi> the <hi>Society,</hi> the <hi>Commerce,</hi> and are Judges and Breakers of the Royal Law, and Deſtroyers of the <hi>Creation</hi> of God, and <hi>Work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manſhip</hi> of his Hands (and Deſtroyers of Natural Affections) which he hath made for his Praiſe, and his Honour, and Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. Neither have they the Mind of Chriſt nor of God guiding of them, who would not have all men to be ſaved;
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:44859:7"/>God would have all the Workmanſhip of his hands, and Creation, and Works to be ſaved, which is man and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man; Chriſt indeed came to deſtroy the Devil and his works, who made man and woman imperfect, who were God's works; ſo the promiſe of God was to mankind, but not unto the Devil; and that his head ſhould be bruiſed, his power broken, and his Law of Sin, and Death, and Members ſhould be diſannulled, and Chriſt's Power, and his Law of Life, Faith, and Love, ſhould be ſet up amongſt God's Creatures, which are his Creation; and ſo Chriſt came to ſave Mens lives, and not to deſtroy them?</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>Now if any ſhould object, and ſay, Who are our Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Firſt all Nations of Men God hath made of one Mould, to dwell upon the ſace of the Earth, <hi>Acts</hi> 17. ſo I ſay, all are Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God by creation, and there is a Brother-hood which by the Royal Law is preſerved according to the Principle of God in every Man, by which they ſhould do unto all their Brethren, as they would have them do unto them.</p>
            <p n="2">2d. They are Sons of God by adoption, all being born again of the Immortal Seed of the Word of God that lives, abides, and endures forever; and being led by the Spirit of God, are Sons of God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.</p>
            <p>Alſo it may be ſeen and taken notice of, what the Apoſtle lays down in <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.2. wherein he ſpeaks to them, who were once Heathens, but then converted; That in times paſt they walkt accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the courſe of this World, according to the Prince of the Power of the Air, the ſpirit that now worketh in the Children of Diſobedience — in the Luſt of the Fleſh, fulfilling the deſires of the Fleſh, and of the Minde, and were by Nature the Children of Wrath as well as others. Now mark, theſe Heathens be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore converſion, there was ſomething in them, that did diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obey, and therein did not fulfill the Will of God, but ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled the will of the Fleſh, and walked according to the luſt of the ſame, which brought them by that nature to be Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Wrath: Now had they obeyed that which they did diſobey, they had not walkt according to the Power of the Prince of the Air, but walkt according to the Prince of the Power of Life, Chriſt Jeſus: and ſo by that which they do diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey, they would have come to have known the Royal Law, to do
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:44859:8"/>unto others, as they would have others do unto them: but none can fulfill this Royal Law of God, that fulfills the Luſt of the Fleſh, and walks according to that Will, which makes them Children of Wrath by Nature: ſo then all people muſt come to that which they have diſobeyed, and ſtill do diſobey; then they will walk according to the Will of God, and the Royal Law of God, and not according to the Prince of the Power of the Air; for all they that diſobey, and walk according to the Prince and Power of the Air, have not affections to Nature, but they walk according to that Prince and Power of the Air, who deſtroyeth Nature in themſelves, and then the Nature of others without them; and theſe have not affections to Nature, Natural Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in themſelves, nor to them without, and are out of the Royal Law of God, viz. to do unto others, as they would have others do unto them; now the Religions, Worſhips and Wayes of ſuch, are no Religions, Wayes, nor Worſhips of God, who do diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey the Spirit of God in their own ſelves, and ſuch do not come to this Noble Royal Law, and Royal Society in it, wherein all men might commune, commerce, and hold correſpondency with all Man-kind, and one with another.</p>
            <p>We read in <hi>Neh.</hi> 9.20. how the Lord gave the Children of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi> his good Spirit to inſtruct them, but in the 28th. verſe 'tis recorded, how that they were diſobedient, and rebelled againſt the Spirit of the Lord, and caſt the Law behind their backs, and ſlew the Prophets of the Lord, which teſtified againſt them, &amp;c. Now mark, after they had rebelled againſt the Spirit of God, and diſobeyed the Lord, they caſt the Law of God behind their backs, and ſlew the Lord's Prophets that teſtified againſt them, and came to turn them to God again.</p>
            <p>Now but conſider whether or no, this hath not been your Work in <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> nay, you have been more dark then theſe <hi>Jews,</hi> and worſe; for you that be the Teachers in <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> ſay, that every Man and Woman hath not the Spirit of God to rebel againſt, and God hath not given to every Man and Woman his Spirit; and therefore you preach up Rebellion, who are found all in the Diſobedience and Rebellion to the Spirit of God in your ſelves, that he hath given to inſtruct you: and likewiſe, alſo you rebel againſt the Spirit of God, that he hath given to others
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:44859:8"/>inſtruct them with; ſo by that you not only caſt away the Royal Law of God behind your backs your ſelves, but are alſo a means to bring others to diſobedience to do the ſame; and this Royal Law being caſt behind your backs both of <hi>Chriſtian</hi> and of <hi>Jew,</hi> you are out of the Royal Society and concord, in which you might commerce together among your ſelves; and not only ſo, but with all Nations that obey the ſame Principle of God in them.</p>
            <p>But all you <hi>Chriſtians, Jews, Turks and Heathens,</hi> that diſobey the good Spirit which God hath given you to inſtruct you, you do caſt the Royal Law behind your Backs, and then you follow all your Wayes, Religions and Worſhips; and then are peeviſh about them, and for them perſecute others, with a diſobedient ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, that will not conform to them, and to you; and deſtroy people, as the <hi>Jews</hi> did, that would not conform.</p>
            <p>So in that (as I ſaid before) you deſtroy God's Creatures which he hath created; and the Works of his Hands; and ſo in that is manifeſted, that you have no natural Affections, nor no Love to God, nor his Royal Law; being diſobedient to the Spirit of God? which would lead you to his Law, <hi>To do unto all as, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In this you might keep a Correſpondency, <hi>viz.</hi> In this Royal Law, one with another, I ſay, above all your Religions, Wayes and Worſhips: And if you all lived in this Royal Law, both <hi>Jews, Turks, Heathens</hi> and <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> ſo called, your Religions, Wayes and Worſhips would all fall to the Ground: For in this Royal Law all Men and Women would have Liberty in a common Society, and common Commerce, and in the Worſhip of God, and might receive a Religion pure from above; for Religions, Wayes, and Worſhips are below, of mens making, which are Works of their own hands, about which they do perſecute their Fellow-creatures, and their Brethren. And alſo, Such as grieve the Spirit, quench and vex the Spirit of God, ſignifying that they have a Meaſure of it; elſe, how could they quench, vex and grieve it? ſo quenching, grieving and vexing that which would lead them unto the Royal Law, <hi>To do unto others as they, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And that ſpirit that quencheth and vexeth the Spirit of God in them will never lead them to the Royal Law of God, but lead them to do ſuch things as they would not that others ſhould do
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:44859:9"/>unto them; but they would judge it hard meaſure, if others ſhould do unto them as they do unto others. And ſo all they (let them be <hi>Chriſtians, Jews, Turks</hi> or <hi>Heathens</hi>) who quench, vex, and grieve the Spirit of God, and ſet up Religions of their own, and are peeviſh about them, to force and draw others to them; thoſe have neither Affections to Nature, nor Natural Affections; but are in that ſpirit that deſtroys Nature, and the Affections to it; and ſuch do to others as they would not have them do unto them, and come not up to that Royal Law, <hi>To do unto all men as they would have them do unto them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And alſo you may read of ſome, <hi>That turned the Grace of God unto Wantonneſs, and walked deſpightfully againſt the Spirit of Grace, and hating the Light,</hi> as you may ſee, <hi>John</hi> 3.19, 20. <hi>Jude</hi> 4. and in other places.</p>
            <p>Now their hating the Light ſignifieth that they had it; for Chriſt ſaith, <hi>They would not come to the Light, leſt their deeds ſhould be reproved;</hi> that is, by the Light; and therefore it was their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation.</p>
            <p>So all Religions, Wayes and Worſhips, whatever men make, that hate the Light, they are made in Darkneſs; both they and thoſe are condemned, as in <hi>John.</hi> 3. So every man that comes into the World being inlightened by Chriſt, the Heavenly Man; <hi>in whom was Life, and this Life was the Light of Men;</hi> ſo every man that cometh into the World, being turned to this Light, they are turned to Chriſt, they are turned to this Royal Law, <hi>To do unto all men as they would have them do unto them;</hi> for there's the Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: Now this ſhews, that every Man and Woman that comes into the World is inlightened with the divine Light of the Heavenly Man, Chriſt Jeſus; which while they hate it, they break the Society with their Fellow-creatures, who are of God's Creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; as alſo the civil Commerce and Correſpondence one with another. And none that hate the Light have Affections to God, to Chriſt, Affections to his Royal Law, or Affections to a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Communion, or Affections to Nature it ſelf; or his Creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; for they that hate the Light, are under the Power of the Prince of Darkneſs, to wit, the Devil, who is the Deſtroyer; and his work as well as theirs is to deſtroy th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s Royal Society; yea, and Nature it ſelf, and God's Creatures, which are the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:44859:9"/>Works of his hands? and thoſe works of theirs are not of God; and the Grace of God, which hath appeared unto all men, Mark, all men whom this Grace brings Salvation to.</p>
            <p>Now they that turn this Grace of God into Wantonneſs, and walk deſpightfully againſt the Spirit of Grace, they have no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to Salvation in themſelves, nor to others, nor no Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to God, nor to Nature: but in that corrupt nature that walks deſpightfully againſt the Spirit of God; ſuch, as I ſaid before, do deſtroy the Natural Affections, which ſhould be amongſt all the Creatures of God in the whole World: that is to ſay, All Mankind, all Men and Women, ſuch as turn the Grace of God into Wantonneſs, they live wantonly, they live ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, they live unrighteouſly, they live in the Luſts of the World, and have a heap of Teachers after this Luſt that they live in, and not after Chriſt. And ſuch as ſet up Religions, that turn the Grace of God into Wantonneſs, and ſay, <hi>That every one hath it not;</hi> and ſo denying the Doctrine of the Apoſtle, and of Salvation; they ſet up their own Doctrine, Religion, Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips, and Wayes, and Force and compel people to them, in which there is no Salvation; and ſay, <hi>There is no Aſſurance there:</hi> And ſuch as do turn this Grace of God unto Wantonneſs are never like to come to the Royal Law of God, in that ſtate, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>To do unto all men as they would have, &amp;c.</hi> For they that turn the Grace of God unto Wantonneſs, do unto others as they would not have others do unto them; and ſo rend from the Royal Society, in the Royal Law: For the Grace of God is the Saints Teacher, which brings the Salvation, and teaches them to live <hi>Soberly, Righteouſly, and Godlikely, &amp;c.</hi> and brings them to know the Royal Law, and to do and fulfil the Royal Law, viz. <hi>To do un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to others as they would have others do unto them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now by all you may ſee its clear, that there is ſomething of God in all Mankind to witneſs the Spirit; and every one that comes into the World are enlightned by Chriſt, the ſecond <hi>Adam:</hi> And the Grace of God hath appeared unto all men, to teach them, and will bring them Salvation; but they that forſake this Grace, and turn it unto Wantonneſs, they turn that unto Wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonneſs, and forſake that that ſhould teach them, and bring their Salvation; yea, I ſay, teach them <hi>to do that unto all as, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:44859:10"/>
            <p>And likewiſe you may ſee in <hi>John</hi> 3.16, where its ſaid, <hi>God ſo loved the World, that he gave his only begotten Son, that whoſoever be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves in him ſhould not periſh, but have Everlaſting Life: And God ſent not his Son into the World to condemn the World, but that the World through him might be ſaved.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This was the World of Mankind (for the Devil, he came to deſtroy, and leads men into Deſtruction, and aſtray from God) that Chriſt comes to ſave; and that through Jeſus Chriſt they might be redeemed, and brought into an Accord, and into a Unity one with another, and with the Son that ſaves them, and with the Father who ſent his Son; and he would that all men ſhould be ſaved in that: 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.3, 4, 5, &amp;c. <hi>For this is good and acceptable in the Sight of God our Saviour, who will have all men to be ſaved, and come to the Knowledge of his Truth; for there is one God, and one Mediator between God and man, the Man Chriſt Jeſus, who gave himſelf a Ranſom for all, to be teſtified in due time.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now here you may ſee the general and univerſal Love of God in Chriſt towards all Mankind, to all his Creatures that he hath created, that he would have all men to be ſaved, and come to the knowledge of his Truth; for he taſted Death for every man, as Scripture of Truth ſaith, which was to be teſtified in due time. And ſo whoſoever is againſt this Doctrine, are the Deceivers and Makers of Sects, and do ſtop or abridge people from coming to that which they have a Right unto, viz. <hi>To him that was a Ranſom for them, and who is their Mediator.</hi> Now he being given a Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom for all, that is for all without exception; and he that hath given himſelf a Ranſom for all, would have all to come to the knowledge of the truth of this.</p>
            <p>So then they would by this means come to the Royal Law and to the Royal Society indeed, which is above all Societies that Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Peoples, Tongues and Languages have made, in all which th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e is Diſcord; but there is no Diſcord in this Royal Law, which brings all people <hi>to do unto others as they, &amp;c.</hi> For here in this are Natural Affections, Affections of Nature to that which God hath created, to wit. Man and Woman, who are made af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his Similitude; ſo that they would not have them deſtroyed, nor hurt; but they will do in this Royal Law unto all Men and Women that are made after the Similitude of God, as they in that
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:44859:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>Similitude ſhould do unto them, that are in the ſame Similitude.</p>
            <p>And further, ſaith the Apoſtle, in 1 <hi>John</hi> 1.1, 2. <hi>We have an Advocate with the Father, Jeſus Chriſt the Righteous; and he is the Propitiation for our Sins, and not for ours only, but for the Sins of the whole World.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now mark, This is a large word for all people to take notice of, <hi>That Chriſt Jeſus is the Propitiation for the ſins of the whole world,</hi> Therefore every one of you in your own particulars, know this That Chriſt Jeſus, who is crowned with Glory and Honour, did taſte Death for every man: Mark, for every man; and whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver denies this Doctrine is an Antichriſt, and preaches another, is a falſe Preacher and Seducer, and brings people to trouble and loſs, from that which is right, and their due, in which is their Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction: So theſe are univerſal things to all Mankind, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by all Mankind might come out of the Earthly old <hi>Adam</hi> in the Fall and Tranſgreſſion, to him that hath dyed for them all, and purchaſt them all, and taſted Death for all, and enlightned them all, and gave his Grace to them all; and he willeth that all might be ſaved, and come to the Knowledge of the Truth of Chriſt, who doth this: And whoever teacheth another doctrine brings people into Sects and Confuſion, to deſtroy one another, where they have not Natural Affections, and will do that to another which they would not have others do unto them, who break the Bonds thereby of civil Commerce amongſt Mankind; and the religions, wayes and worſhips of all ſuch, are no Worſhips, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligions, nor VVayes to God; but ſet up by a dark peeviſh ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, by which they deſtroy one another, which are God's Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, about them; all which come from him who is out of Truth, whom Chriſt came to deſtroy.</p>
            <p>VVe have likewiſe another Expreſſion of the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> to the buſineſs in hand, in 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.9, 10. <hi>This is</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>a faithful Saying, and worthy of all Acceptation; for therefore we both labour and ſuffer Reproach, becauſe we truſt in the Living God, who is the Saviour of all men, eſpecially of them that believe: theſe things com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand and teach.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mark now, that whoſoever doth teach the contrary, he is a falſe Teacher, and his Doctrine is falſe; for this is a great word, <hi>He was the Saviour of all men, eſpecially them that believe;</hi> and they
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:44859:11"/>that taught this did ſuffer Reproach, and were rebuk't by them that oppoſed this Doctrine; as they that preach this Doctrine now are reproacht, and ſuffer by the Oppoſers of it now; and thoſe that are the Oppoſers of it now, are thoſe that keep people from their Salvation, yea, from God, and from Chriſt: And ſuch are they that are Makers of Sects, and then deſtroy one another about them, who have no Natural Affections, and do not to others as they would have others do unto them.</p>
            <p>And Chriſt Jeſus ſaith, <hi>He came to call ſinners to Repentance,</hi> that were in the old <hi>Adam,</hi> that they might change from the old earthly <hi>Adam,</hi> and turn to Chriſt, the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> the Heavenly Man.</p>
            <p>Now they that ſtopt their Ears and clos'd their Eyes then, they were the greateſt Profeſſors upon the Earth; and ſo they are now, and the Higheſt Prieſts: For by it is ſignified, that there is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in them that they ſhould ſee withal, and hear withal; and ſuch as did ſo, had no Affections to Nature, nor to the Royal Law of God, nor to Chriſt, neither then, nor now, to do to others as they would have others do unto them.</p>
            <p>And Chriſt Jeſus ſaith, <hi>Mark</hi> 13.37, <hi>What I ſay unto you, I ſay unto all, Watch:</hi> Intimating as if there was ſomething of God in them, by which they muſt watch againſt ſomething that was not of God in them, but of the Devil, the Tempter, who is out of the Truth, and tempts men that they ſhould not walk in the Way of Truth; ſo they that were tempted, and obeyed him, went from their watch; and thoſe ſtop their Ears, and cloſe their Eyes from the Spirit of God in them.</p>
            <p>As alſo thoſe whom Chriſt calls, <hi>Ravening Wolves inwardly,</hi> who come to be like a Thiſtle and Thorny-Tree, that did deceive men; when they went out to gather Figs or Grapes from them, they could meet with nothing but Thorns and Thiſtles: And as ſuch then, ſo now are the greateſt Profeſſors in the World, but inwardly ravening Wolves, who were ravened from the Life; and the Wolves, and Thiſtles, and Bryars will hurt and deſtroy Nature. And ſo it is the ſpirit of the Devil that makes them Wolves, and it is the Spirit of God that makes them Lambs: and therefore theſe Wolves, Thiſtles, and Bryars, are ſuch as have not the leaſt Practice of the Royal Law of God among them, <hi>in doing unto all as they would have all men do unto them.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:44859:11"/>
            <p>But yet this denotes, that there was ſomething in theſe Wolves that they were ravened from, that would have kept them and led them to the Royal Law of God, namely, as I ſaid, <hi>To do unto all as they would have all do unto them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For they would not have Thorns and Thiſtles to prick and tear them, like a Woolf, in pieces; and therefore, if they will be obedient unto that which they are ravened from, and come to it again, it will lead them. To do unto others, &amp;c. Not to thiſtle prick, and worry others; for they would not be ſo done to themſelves: ſo that this brings to the Royal Society, in the Royal Law of God, where all Mankind might keep a Concord.</p>
            <p>And ſaith the Lord, in <hi>Exod.</hi> 23.4, 5. <hi>If thou meeteſt with thine Enemies Ox or his Aſs going aſtray, thou ſhalt ſurely bring it back again to him. If thou ſeeſt the Aſs of him that hates thee lying under his Burden, and ſhalt forbear to help him, thou ſhalt ſurely help with him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mark the Law and Command of God, this was an Enemies Aſs, and an Enemies Ox; much more the Beaſt of a Friend, and thoſe <hi>Jews</hi> that were called the Children of God; but how ſhort are <hi>Chriſtians</hi> of this very thing, in that many of them will, and do put the Cattel of them that are call'd <hi>Chriſtians</hi> aſtray, turn them out of way on purpoſe: But here are three things.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Here is that that will overcome the Enemy. 2d. Here is that that will preſerve the Creation of God. 3d. That here they ſhould do to others, as they would have others do unto them; for the Law of God, which was the ſame to the <hi>Jews,</hi> is alſo the ſame unto the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> that were among them: ſo one Law was to thoſe that were within, and to thoſe that were without; for this Law of God, which was, and is called the Royal Law, to wit, to do to all men, as they, &amp;c. that is, to do that which is Righteous, Juſt, Holy, and Good unto all Men, as they would have all Men do Righteouſly, Juſtly, Holily, and do that onely which is good, &amp;c. and now in ſo doing, this will keep up a Juſt, Holy, Righteous, and a good Society amongſt Man-kinde: and this was the Law that was added becauſe of Tranſgreſſion, the Tranſgreſſion of the Command of God, by which Man loſt the Image of God; he loſt Righteouſneſs, and Holineſs, and that Power that gave him Dominion <hi>Gal</hi> 3.19. therefore the Law was added upon man, when he had loſt Righteouſneſs, and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:44859:12"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:44859:12"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:44859:13"/>the Image of God, and the Power of God within him: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Juſt, Holy, Good and Righteous Law of the higher Power, I ſay, was added becauſe of Tranſgreſſion, upon Man and Woman; which Juſt, Righteous, Good and Holy Law, anſwers the Good, the Juſt, the Righteous, and the Holy Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of God in every man, that they have tranſgreſt. So now, if they come to that again, which they have tranſgreſt, and to obey the Good, Juſt, Righteous and Holy Law of Liberty, they come to the Holy Society, and Holy Communion and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord: and ſo this Juſt, Good, Holy, and Righteous Law is over all Tranſgreſſors, whether they be <hi>Chriſtians, Turks, Jews,</hi> or <hi>Heathens:</hi> It anſwers I ſay, the Good and Righteous Principle in them, that they have tranſgreſt; now would they but minde that good Principle in them, that brings them to the Good and Righteous Law; it will bring them to do to all men, as they would, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Now this Law commands to entertain Strangers; for ſaith the Lord, <hi>You were Strangers in Egypt, and there you were entertained; and therefore do unto others, as you would be done to by them; relieve the Fatherleſs, for your Children may be Fatherleſs; and would you not have them reliev'd? relieve the Widdows, for your Wives may be Wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows; and would you not have them to be relieved in caſe of neceſſity?</hi> So do unto all, as you would have them do unto you. Again, you would have none to kill you, or to covet your Goods, or to ſteal from you; you would have none to commit Adultry with your Wives, or defile your Children; which things are an Abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination unto the Lord; therefore do not you ſo to any others, but mind the Righteous Law that anſwers the Righteous Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of God in you, that keeps you in Holineſs, and Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, that is good; and in this you will have eſteem of God, and his Royal Law; and will have an eſteem of your Souls and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, which are the Lords, that they may be kept holy, that ſo they may be an acceptable Offering unto the Lord, who is holy, whoſe they are; for Chriſt came to deſtroy the Devil and his Works, who had ſowed the evil Seed of Diſcord among the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of men, who are the Creation of God, his Creatures: And Chriſt that came to redeem man, and ſave him, ſayes, <hi>Love your Enemies, and love one another, for that is of God;</hi> then Hatred and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:44859:13"/>Enmity is not of God: ſo here they were to love the Creature<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> but not the Evil; for the Creatures were of God's Creation; for Chriſt came to deſtroy the Devil, and not Man-kind, but that onely which would deſtroy them. This is the General and Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Love; for God ſo loved the World, in ſending his Son into the World, when <hi>Jews,</hi> and <hi>Gentiles</hi> were concluded under Sin, to be an Offering, and Sacrifice for the ſins of the whole World: And therefore Chriſt Jeſus ſaith, <hi>Love one another and love Enemies;</hi> for that ſhews, and anſwers the Mind of God, and of Chriſt, who lays down his Life for Enemies, and dies for Sinners; and ſo loved the World, though they were Enemies, that he ſent his Son into the World, that the World through him might live; and ſo God was in Chriſt reconciling the World unto himſelf; and God cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth his Son to ſhine upon the Juſt, and the Unjuſt, and the Rain to fall upon the Good, and the Evil, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.44, 45.</p>
            <p>So here is the Univerſal Love of God to Man-kind, his Son ſhines upon the Unjuſt Man's Field, as well as on the Juſt Man's, and his Rain falls upon the Unjuſt Man's Ground, as well as on the Juſt Man's: And therefore you ſhould be of the ſame mind with Chriſt, for that was the end of his ſpeaking thoſe words, that ſo you might go, and do likewiſe. If your rain do not fall upon the Unjuſt Man's Field, as upon the Juſt, you are the wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring Clouds, that are ſaid to have no Water in them, and ſo deceive people; and your Sun is turned to Darkneſs, that think it ſhines upon no Body but your ſelves.</p>
            <p>So you be out of Chriſt's Doctrine, that do not practice his, namely, to love Enemies, and to have your Rain, and your Sun; if your Rain be from God, and your Sun be from God, it will ſhine upon the Unjuſt as well as upon the Juſt, even for their good; and it will fall upon the Unjuſt, and the Juſt, I mean the Rain: now they that have not this, let them profeſs what they will, God's words and Chriſt's words, they are Hypocrites, and are blind Guides, that lead into the Ditch.</p>
            <p>Now the Lord ſaith, <hi>Thou ſhalt love thy Neighbour as thy ſelf;</hi> and ſo commands his Law.</p>
            <p>Mark, Thy Neighbour thou ſhalt love as thy ſelf; for all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of men hath God made of one Blood and one Mould to dwell upon the Face of the Earth: So mark, they are made of one
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:44859:14"/>ſo there is the Natural Affections out of that one, to the one, all men made of one; and there comes the love to his Neighbour, of the ſame Blood and Mould as himſelf; and there comes the Royal Law to be received, to do to all men of the ſame Blood and Mould of the Lord's making, as he would have them do unto him.</p>
            <p>And whoſoever profeſſeth godlineſs and chriſtianity, or God, or Chriſt, or whatſoever other Religion in the whole World, and do not love their Neighbour as themſelves; and all being made of one Blood and Mould on the face of the Earth, they are all Breakers of the Law of God, and Diſhonourers of God, and are Hypocrites that do profeſs the Law and Goſpel, that come ſhort of this, and do not practice, that is to ſay, love your Neighbours as your ſelves, and are out of the Royal Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety, and the Royal Law: And whatſoever Religion, Way, or Worſhip people have made, and are out of this, that is to ſay, Love thy Neighbour as thy ſelf, and do unto all men, as they would have them do unto them; their Religion, Way, and Worſhip, is no Religion, it is but Vanity, and their profeſſion of God and Chriſt is but Vanity and Hypocriſie, and do call upon God with their Lips, and their Hearts are far off from him, and his Royal Law; and ſuch deſtroy Natural Affections, and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture it ſelf; for they that love their Neighbour as themſelves, (which is above all the Religions in the World of mens making) do ſhew forth Natural Affections, if they love their Neighbours as themſelves, which is the general Command.</p>
            <p>And in this here is a general Unity, a general Concord, a general Commerce and Correſpondency with all their Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours in the whole World, neighbour Nations, neighbour Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, neighbour Towns.</p>
            <p>And 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.13. <hi>Honour all men, love the Brother-hood, fear God, honour the King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now to honour all men, is to have all men in eſteem, as you may read, and if I eſteem all men, I ſhall certainly hurt no man, neither would I have any other to hurt any man, or to hurt one another; for I eſteem and honour them, Why? Becauſe they are of God's Creation, and God's Creatures, and made after the Similitude of God, and therefore I am to honour them all.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:44859:14"/>2d, <hi>To love the Brotherhood;</hi> thoſe that are Brethren, born again and begotten again of the immortal Seed, which are living Stones, and made a Spiritual Houſhold of Brethren.</p>
            <p n="3">3d, <hi>Fear God, Honour the King;</hi> ſo there's none can honour the King, but thoſe that fear God; and none can fear God, who live in Evil and in Sin.</p>
            <p>And in <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.14. the Spirit of God by the Apoſtle com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands us, <hi>To follow Peace with all men;</hi> and elſewhere ſaith he, <hi>Seek the Peace of all men, and the Good of all men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So now mind this, All men muſt ſeek the Good of one another, one anothers Peace, which is in Chriſt Jeſus (not in old <hi>Adam</hi>) and in his Royal Law, in which they may come to a Concord, and demonſtrate a Natural Affection, and divine Affections to all men, who ſeek the Peace of all men: And they that ſeek the Peace of all men, they will not ſeek their Trouble, nor Captivity, nor their Slavery, nor their Hurt, but their Eternal Good, and Eternal Peace; and this is that that is wanting among them, that have been Profeſſors of <hi>Chriſtianity.</hi> So they that have profeſt, and not in the Poſſeſſion of this, in not ſeeking the Peace of all men, are Hypocrites; to ſeek the Peace of <hi>Jew, Gentile, Heathen,</hi> and all men; for they are the Workmanſhip of God, God's Creatures, and their Fellow-creatures, made of the ſame Fleſh and Mould to dwell upon the Face of the Earth: and they that be out of this, whatever Worſhip, Profeſſion, or Religion they are of, its worth nothing.</p>
            <p>And ſaith the Apoſtle further in 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.12. <hi>For we dare not make our ſelves of the number, or compare our ſelves with ſome, that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend themſelves; but they meaſuring themſelves by themſelves, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring themſelves amongſt themſelves, are not wiſe: But we will not boaſt of things without our Meaſure, but according to the Meaſure of the Rule which God hath diſtributed to us, a meaſure even to reach unto you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now this Rule, this Meaſure, was the Spirit of God, by which they reacht unto the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> by which they were one anothers Epiſtle to one anothers Hearts, and known and read of all men. Now they that meaſure themſelves by themſelves, and compare themſelves among themſelves, which was not Wiſdom, they were without this Rule, and this Spirit, and Meaſure: As now look over all <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> and you ſhall find them without this Meaſure and
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:44859:15"/>this Rule, who ſay, <hi>The Letter is the Rule;</hi> and are broken into ſo many Sects one againſt another, meaſuring themſelves and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring themſelves with themſelves, which are not wiſe; for none are made wiſe but by the Spirit of God, which is indeed the Rule and the Meaſure; and that is it which brings, <hi>To do unto all men as they would have them do unto them;</hi> to that Royal Law, and Royal Liberty, and Royal Society; and they that do ſo, do ſhew their Loyalty and Obedience unto God and his Law.</p>
            <p>So all people in the whole World, of what Sect, or Worſhip or Religion ſoever, they muſt come to their meaſure of the Spirit of God, and ſo to the Rule; and lay away their own Rule, that they rule things by, and rule their religions by, and their wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips by, and righteouſneſs by, that they have made; and lay aſide their Meaſure, by which they have meaſured their religions, and worſhips, and their Righteouſneſs, and have meaſured others. Now if People would not come according to their Meaſure, and their Rule, they have been ready to deſtroy God's Creatures, who are made after the ſimilitude of God, and to curſe them, and to damn them: This is the Practice of ſuch that meaſure with their own Meaſure, and that walk according to their own Rule, who have not Natural Affections, that do come to the Royal Law and Liberty: Therefore all, I ſay, muſt lay aſide their own meaſure and rule, and come to the Spirit of God, and ſo to the Rule, which is the Spirit of God, by which they may come to the Royal Law of God, and ſo to the Royal Society, and ſo to the Natural Affections, to the Divine and Natural Affections.</p>
            <p>And that of the Apoſtle in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. is very remarkable, where the Apoſtle ſpeaks of Love, which ought to be amongſt all <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> who profeſs the Name of Chriſt; which Love, if a man hath not, he is nothing, nay, his Religion and Worſhip is nothing; yea, if he hath Faith, it is nothing, if he hath not Love; if he (ſaith he) hath Knowledge, and knows Secrets, if he (ſaith he) hath Propheſie, if he ſpeaks with Tongues, and hath not Love, all is nothing; and ſo his Profeſſion is nothing.</p>
            <p>So all ye Schollars, all ye Sects in the whole <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> if you have not this Love, if out of it, all that you have is nothing; if you feed the poor, and give your Body to be burnt, and will burn others, all this will profit you nothing, if (I ſay) you have not
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:44859:15"/>Love; Love to one onother, Love to God, Love to Chriſt, Love to Enemies, Natural Affection, through which you will not deſtroy Nature; you will not deſtroy God's Creatures, God's Creation, Man and Woman, whom God hath made after his own Similitude. Ye profeſs ye love God, and yet hate your Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren (for ye are all Brethren in <hi>Adam</hi>) you are all Lyars; for <hi>how can you love God whom you ſee not, and hate your Brother whom you do ſee daily.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now this Love it ſuffers long, and is curteous and kind, and envieth not God's Creatures, God's Creation, Man and Woman, who are (I ſay) made after the Similitude of God: It doth not behave it ſelf unſeemly, whereas they that are out of this Love behave themſelves unſeemly, and are not curteous and kind, which are the works of the Fleſh.</p>
            <p>Now Love ſeeks not her own, nor is ſhe eaſily provoked, think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth no Evil: Now they that be out of this Love, are eaſily pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vokt, think Evil, and do it; ſeek their own Welfare, and not the Welfare of another; their own Good, and not the Good of another.</p>
            <p>Love bears all things, believes all things, hopes all things: Whereas they that are out of Love cannot believe all things, nor hope all things, nor cannot endure all things; full of Unbelief, and Impatience; now this is that that hath been wanting in <hi>Chriſtendom:</hi> and who be out of this Love, though they may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs Chriſt, and the Prophets and Apoſtles words, yet all their Profeſſion is nothing; and ſuch as be in this Love have Natural Affections, and do not deſpiſe the Royal Law of God, nor his Creatures, viz. <hi>To do to all as we would have all do to us:</hi> And none come to receive this Love, but thoſe alone who come to the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of God in themſelves in their Meaſure.</p>
            <p>And alſo, for further Proof, you may ſee in the Scriptures of Truth, how thoſe whom you ſtile <hi>Heathens,</hi> many of them that ſpeak good of God, and of his Kingdom, which they could not do without the Spirit of God; as what <hi>Abimilech</hi> ſpoke to <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham;</hi> and the King of the <hi>Philiſtines</hi> to <hi>Iſaac; Pharaoh</hi> to <hi>Joſeph,</hi> as alſo <hi>Potiphar</hi> his firſt Maſter; and the very Goaler was ſenſible of God's being with <hi>Joſeph</hi> in Priſon, and bleſſing him; ſo likewiſe <hi>Cyrus,</hi> and King <hi>Darius</hi> ſpake good of God; and <hi>Nebuchadnezar</hi> in
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:44859:16"/>his Dream ſaw Chriſt and his Kingdom; <hi>Cornelius</hi> we read in the <hi>Acts</hi> prayed to God, though a <hi>Heathen;</hi> and the Queen of the South acknowledged the Lord; likewiſe <hi>Rahab</hi> the Harlot, who entertained the Spies; King <hi>Hyram;</hi> the Marriners with whom <hi>Jonah</hi> was embarqued; not forgetting the King of <hi>Nine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth:</hi> all which (with a Cloud of other Witneſſes, which for bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity we paſs over) denote, that there is ſomething of God in all people; whereas <hi>Chriſtian Profeſſors</hi> and <hi>Jews</hi> fondly imagine, <hi>That none have the Spirit of God, but them;</hi> and ſo theſe &amp; others Scriptures judge them: and theſe are thoſe that make themſelves a Sect, and are the blind Guides, who do not ſee the Seed ſown upon all Grounds, and how the Grace of God that brings Salvation hath appeared unto all men, nor the Light by which Chriſt enlightens every man that comes into the World: So theſe blind guides lead into the Ditch, a corrupting place, and ſee not Chriſt, who taſted Death for every man, and ſhed his Blood for all, and enlightens every man (I ſay) that they might ſee the Salvation, &amp; the Grace, &amp; Truth, that comes by Chriſt, which brings their Salvation. And ſuch as have a Profeſſion of the Letter, <hi>Jew, Chriſtian,</hi> and others, that are not in the Spirit of God, who gave them forth, but in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other dark ſpirit, do not ſee the Spirit that is given to every one to profit withal; and ſo they cannot bring people into that by which they might profit, &amp; come to the Royal Law, <hi>To do unto all as they would have all do unto them;</hi> &amp; ſo to a Royal Society, where they might all honour God, and keep Communion among themſelves.</p>
            <p>Now every Man and Woman in the whole World muſt firſt be turn'd to the Spirit of God in themſelves, that has reproved them, which they have grieved, quencht and vext; and muſt turn to the Light, that they have hated; &amp; turn to the Grace, that appear'd to them, which they have turned unto Wantonneſs, and walkt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpightfully againſt: to this they muſt all turn to, before they come to the Royal Law, that brings them, <hi>To do to all as they, &amp;c.</hi> and ſo to keep the Loyal Law, and holy and juſt Society in the Royal, Holy, and juſt Law. So it is that becauſe both <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Chriſtians</hi> have had the Letter of the Scripture, they have bin envious againſt others, and call them <hi>Heathens;</hi> and becauſe they have the Letter, therefore they thought <hi>None but they had the Spirit, and that the Heathen had it not:</hi> But you may ſee in the Scriptures before men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:44859:16"/>(whom they call Heathen) whether they have the Spirit of God or no; read (I ſay) but the Scriptures before mentioned, and convince your ſelves, and let ſuch ſtop their own mouthes, and ſay with the Apoſtle, <hi>That there is no difference between</hi> Jew <hi>and</hi> Gentile, <hi>who hath the Letter, and he that hath not:</hi> ſo there is no difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Jew</hi> and <hi>Chriſtian</hi> that have the Letter, and <hi>Gentile</hi> now that hath not the Letter, who are without him (to wit) the Spirit of God that gave it forth; for that makes the difference, and is the Leader into all Truth, and to the Royal Law, both <hi>Jew, Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> and <hi>Gentile,</hi> who obey it; and ſo <hi>to do unto all men as they, &amp;c.</hi> and ſo in the holy, juſt and righteous <hi>Royal Law,</hi> to keep a juſt, a righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, and a good Society, that's <hi>Royal,</hi> and have the dominion over all other ſocieties in the whole <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſe</hi> out of this Law: and theſe will come to nothing which are of mens making, though they may hold them up for a time before the National Law; but they will come to an end, if they be not in the <hi>Royal Law</hi> of <hi>Liberty,</hi> where in every man muſt do unto others as he would they ſhould do to him;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Jam.</hi> 3. Where you may ſee how <hi>the nature of Beaſts, and of Birds, and of Serpents, and of things in the Sea, are tamed by the nature of man; but the Tongue of man can no man tame, it is ſuch an unruly Member, full of deadly Porſon; therewith we bleſs God the Father, and therewith curſe we men, who are made after the Similitude and Image of God.</hi> Now con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider all <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> and others, who profeſs Scripture, and all others who have not the Scripture, call'd <hi>Heathens;</hi> yea, conſider this, I ſay, <hi>all mankind upon the face of the Earth,</hi> by whom things in the Sea and in the Earth are tamed; and now ſeeing that your Tongues are untamed, that unruly Member in your ſelves, that is full of <hi>deadly Poyſon,</hi> with which you bleſs God the Father, and with it you curſe man, <hi>who is made after the Image of God;</hi> O do not you all in this <hi>bring a curſe upon your ſelves,</hi> who were made in the <hi>ſame Image</hi> and <hi>Similitude?</hi> and can <hi>you curſe another, and not curſe your ſelves?</hi> Now what is it that muſt tame this unruly Member in your ſelves, that's full of <hi>deadly Poyſon,</hi> and bring it under a Power to tame it? Is it not the <hi>Spirit of God</hi> in the <hi>Jew,</hi> in the <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> and in the <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile</hi> or <hi>Heathen,</hi> by which you may have <hi>power</hi> over your <hi>Tongues,</hi> by Obedience to the Power of God? And therefore the Spirit and Power of God hath a Bridle upon your Tongues, to hold them faſt from Curſing, and all manner of Evil-ſpeaking, whereof you muſt give an Account: And ſo that Power and Spirit
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:44859:17"/>of God in you all, both <hi>Heathen, Jew</hi> and <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> that tames the Tongue, and bridles the Tongne, which brings you to the Royal Law, <hi>To ſpeak and to do to all men, as you would have them ſpeak and to do to you;</hi> ſo that your words may be few, and gratious, and vertuous; that ſo the words of Life may be in your Tongues, which ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers down the Evil, and cuts and burns it out of the Tongue, and comes to be a Bridle and a Bit unto it; that, as was ſaid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, <hi>You may ſpeak and do unto all, as you would have them ſpeak and do unto you.</hi> For mark, <hi>With your Tongues you curſe men, which are made after the Image and Similitude of God; and with the ſame Tongue you bleſs God the Father.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now in this that you curſe men, who are made after the Image and Similitude of God, do you not curſe the Maker? then do not you curſe God? do not you curſe his Image and Similitude, when you curſe Men who are made in the ſimilitude of God? And ſo is that Bleſſing accepted think you of God the Father, in that you bleſs him, and yet curſe that which he hath made in his own Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, after his own Image?</p>
            <p>Now conſider this, Whether this be not the wiſdom from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low in you, that is Deviliſh, Earthly and ſenſual; and ſo would you not have others to curſe you? Would you not be ready to ſay (if they ſhould do it) <hi>They have curſt that that God hath made, and curſt his Image?</hi> And would not you ſay to them; <hi>Though they bleſs God the Father, it is not accepted, when as they curſe you?</hi> And therefore if you fulfil the <hi>Royal Law,</hi> according to the Scripture, <hi>Thou ſhalt love thy Neighbour as thy ſelf,</hi> Jam. 2.</p>
            <p>And ſo he that doth <hi>fulfil</hi> the <hi>Royal Law,</hi> wil not hate his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour; for he would not have his Neighbour hate him, neither will he curſe his Neighbour, nor ſpeak <hi>Evil</hi> of him; for he would not have his Neighbour do ſo to him; and therefore ſo ſpeak, and ſo do: <hi>For Love does not Steal, does not commit Adultery, Love does not. Covet, Love does not bear Falſe Witneſs, and Love ſeeks not her own, Love does not Kill;</hi> and ſo the Law is fulfilled in one word, viz. <hi>Thou muſt love thy Neighbour as thy ſelf, and God above all;</hi> who is over all, bleſſed forever: Now this keeps a Royal Society in the Royal Law of Liberty:</p>
            <p>Chriſt perſecutes no man, for not receiving his Doctrine, nor yet the Apoſtles; and both Chriſt and his Apoſtles gave forth
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:44859:17"/>their Doctrine freely to his People, and the World: Though Chriſt was as good as called (<hi>Mat.</hi> 12.24.) <hi>A Devil, and a Mad-Man, a Blaſphemer, a Deceiver, a Maker of Tumults;</hi> yet he did not exerciſe any Power, or any outward Authority over them (though he had all Power, both in Heaven and in Earth, given unto him) ſo as to impriſon any, or perſecute, or baniſh them; neither did any of thoſe that follow'd him, who did convert people unto God.</p>
            <p>Iſa. 12.5. <hi>Sing unto the Lord; for he hath done excellent things: this is known in all the Earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So then you may ſee, that there is ſomething of God in people, that brings them to know thoſe excellent things, that the Lord has and doth work in the Earth; which if people would but mind ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly, it would lead them to do his Law, <hi>viz. To do unto all, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Jer. 23.23, 24. <hi>Am I a God at hand, ſaith the Lord, and not a God afar off? Can any hide himſelf in ſecret places, that I cannot ſee him, ſaith the Lord? Do not I fill Heaven and Earth, ſaith the Lord?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So the Lord God is the Lord, the Creator of all things in the Heavens, Earth, and in the Sea, ſo then he is Lord of all, and they are all his, and hath created them to his glory: But man, that grieved his Spirit, and tranſgreſſed it, and his Royal Law caſt away, he jars with the Creation of God. And oft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times you may ſee throughout the Scriptures, how the Lord and his Prophets did declare againſt them that did caſt his Royal Law behind their backs.</p>
            <p>So now, if you ſay, <hi>This was in reference to the Jews;</hi> may it not be verified of you called <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> and others? for, <hi>Do you do unto all men as you would have all men do unto you?</hi> Do you keep this Law of Liberty, in which the right Natural Affections are? 'Tis ſaid, <hi>The Jews did caſt the Righteous Law behind their backs, which Law was Juſt, Holy and Good;</hi> and do not you called <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> who profeſs the Goſpel, and others do the ſame, who may be ready to find <hi>Fault</hi> with the <hi>Jews</hi> for doing it? So both you and them have caſt the <hi>Law of God</hi> behind your backs, which (I ſay) is ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, juſt, good and righteous; ſo as you do not to others as you would they ſhould do to you: you have broken the <hi>Royal Society,</hi> you have thrown away <hi>Natural Affections,</hi> you do that that is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt to people, you do that that is not good to them nor righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous; and would you have <hi>all people</hi> do unrighteouſly, and unjuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:44859:18"/>and that that is not good nor holy to you? For, caſting away the Righteous, Good and the Juſt Law behind their backs; you caſt away that whereby you ſhould do that which is Juſt, Righteous and Holy to others. And ſo all your Societies, that are not up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held by this Juſt, Righteous and Holy Law of God, are upheld by that which is not Juſt, nor Righteous, nor Holy, nor Good; ſo that people do that to others that they would not have them do unto them. Mark the End of all that.</p>
            <p>Hab. 3.3. <hi>The Glory of the Lord covered the Heavens, and the Earth was full of his Praiſe, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Zach. 14.9. <hi>And the Lord ſhall be King over all the Earth; in that Day ſhall there be one Lord, and his Name ſhall be one.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And <hi>Gen.</hi> 9.1, 2, &amp;c. where we read, how the Lord God bleſſed <hi>Noah</hi> and his Sons, ſaying unto them, <hi>Bring ye forth Fruit, and multiply, and repleniſh the Earth; and the Fear of you, and the Dread of you, ſhall be upon every Beaſt of the Earth, and upon every Foul of the Air, and upon all that moveth upon the Earth, and upon all the Fiſh of the Sea; into your hands are they delivered: every thing that moveth it ſelf, every thing that liveth, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mark here, God, who is the Creator of all, and the God of the whole Earth, which is full of his Praiſe, and created all things to his Glory, and Man in his Image, and ſet him above all the Works of his Hands, and gave him his Law, by which he was not to oppreſs any Creature that he had created, nor to ſpend them on his Luſt, to the diſhonour of God; and gave him his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, by which he ſhould know his Law, and know him the Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giver: <hi>For that which might be known of God was manifeſt in them, and God hath ſhewed it unto them:</hi> And ſo with this of God in Mankind, he might know his Royal Law, which is juſt, righteous, holy and good, and within the limits of this, that all Mankind do keep a Royal Society, a juſt, good, and holy Royal Society, and do unto all men as they would have them do unto them in all things; for this <hi>Royal Law</hi> teaches ſo to do, in which is the Liberty.</p>
            <p>All people in the whole World conſider, Do not all your Religions, Wayes and Worſhips lie in external and outward things that you have made? and yet many of you <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> and others, will find Fault with others; that is, ſuch that worſhip the works of their own hands: And are not all Religions that are
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:44859:18"/>made (and Worſhips) by men, which are the works of their own hands, in the whole World? And do not every Sect in their Way, Religion and Worſhip do unto another Sect and Religion as they would not have them do unto them? And ſo is not all the Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of people (as you call it) one Sect beget people from ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Sect, and it is but a Sect when all is done; and yet not come to the Royal Law of Liberty, nor yet the Goſpel? For let the eye go over the whole World, and ſee how one Sect ſtrives and and makes it their Buſineſs to pluck from another Sect; and the more People they get, the more Wages, Tythes and Augmentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons they get: So this is not getting people to God, but to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; this is not preaching Chriſt, nor God, but themſelves.</p>
            <p>And now all people but conſider, Has not the Converſion been by outward Powers, by Queens Powers, or Kingly Powers, by States Powers, or by an Emperor's Power, for many Hundreds of Years? For before the Pope got up, did not the <hi>Arian</hi> Hereſie (when he got up I ſay) that is, got the power in his hands, made moſt turn <hi>Arians</hi> by his Sword? inſomuch that it became a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb, <hi>Totus mundus Arianus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And then when the other Power got over <hi>Arian,</hi> then they turn'd from him. And further, When the Pope got up, did not he by his Inquiſition and outward Sword, by his Priſons and Goales convert people unto his Sect and Faction? and this hath been the Converſion all along. And then when the <hi>Turk</hi> got up, did not he by his outward Power convert people to him? yea, many that were <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> were turned by his outward Sword and Power.</p>
            <p>And did not the King of <hi>Spain</hi> convert abundance of <hi>Indians</hi> by his External Power and outward Sword, when he put ſo many to ſeveral ſorts of cruel Deaths, as their own Hiſtorians relate? Now this Converſion was not of God, nor of the Spirit of God, nor of the Word of God, which is the Sword of the Spirit; but by the outward Power and Sword.</p>
            <p>And how have many people been converted in <hi>Germany</hi> think you? Were not many their Converts by the Magiſtrates Sword? and did they not turn as the Magiſtrates did, and as the Pope, and as the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> and King of <hi>France?</hi> Was not there once a King of <hi>France</hi> a <hi>Proteſtant?</hi> and did not he turn? and how many did turn with him?</p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:44859:19"/>
            <p>And how many were converted by <hi>Henry</hi> the eighth from the Pope, by his regal Sword and Power? yea, how many Prieſts and People? And ſo likewiſe, how many turned <hi>Proteſtants</hi> in his Son <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixth Reign, which was not long? And then how many turn'd <hi>Papiſts</hi> again in his Siſter Queen <hi>Mary</hi>'s Reign, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately after his deceaſe? for did ſhe not by her Power con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert both Prieſts and People to the Pope? And ſhortly after, How many did Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> convert from <hi>Popery</hi> to <hi>Proteſtancy,</hi> both of Prieſts and People? Thouſands of Thouſands.</p>
            <p>So were not all theſe converted by the Laws and outward Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers all along, ſince that Converſion has been loſt by the Power and Spirit of God, that the Apoſtles were in, in their Day, by which (I ſay) they did convert people to God; and not by the Magiſtrates Sword, nor by humane coercive Laws, contrary to a mans Conſcience.</p>
            <p>And how did the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> convert to their Directory from the Common-Prayer, by vertue of their outward Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and Sword, when they had in this laſt Age got it into their hands? And how many did the <hi>Independants</hi> convert to their Church-Faith, from the <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> and from others, when he had got the Sword and Power into his hands? And now how many have the Common-Prayer-men got back again by their Power &amp; outward Sword, when they had got it into their hands, both from the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> Directory, and <hi>Independant</hi> Church-Faith, &amp;c. to the Common-Prayer again? So that much of the Converſion ſince the Apoſtles days, or about this Thouſand Years, have been by outward Law and coercive Power, by Priſons, Inquiſitions, Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, Fire and Faggot, &amp;c. and by this means they have forced men to their Religions, that they have made, contrary to their Conſciences; and have done to others, as they would not have others do the ſame thing to them.</p>
            <p>And ſo the Prieſts turn'd with the Magiſtrates, and preacht ſtif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly againſt that that they preacht up not long before, and preacht up that now that once they preacht againſt; this has been clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſeen? And ſo as one Power has got up, by the Sword and the Law, they have put down other Religions, that were ſet up by Law and the Sword; and if others ſhould get over them, then they would put down their Religions, and ſet up again Religions
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:44859:19"/>and Worſhips of their own: And ſo men make Religions, and then ſet them up, and then again others in power put them down; and men open mens Mouthes, and others ſtop their Mouthes that formerly had preacht; and ſo men are put up and pluckt down, ſo as every man is uncertain in his Religion and Worſhip, and knows not what may be ſet up in a year, or what Religion or Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip he may be forced to conform to, or ſuffer in not doing of it.</p>
            <p>So happy are they that are in the Religion that cometh down from above, and in the Worſhip that Chriſt Jeſus ſet up above One Thouſand Six Hundred Years ſince, that Heavenly Man, that changeth not; who is yeſterday, to day, and forever the <hi>Alpha</hi> and <hi>Omega.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now if all the people in the World, who are in ſo many Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions, Wayes and Worſhips, would come to the Principle of God in them, by which they may come to the Royal Law, and <hi>to do unto all men as you would have all men do unto you;</hi> you would come to the Royal Society, and the Fellowſhip in the Royal Law, which is far above all the Fellowſhips and Societies in all the Religions, Wayes and Worſhips that they have made and ſet up, where they <hi>do not do to others, as they would have others do to them:</hi> For when one Religion is put down, and another ſet up, that which is put down is oft times called Hereſie: And again, when at any time that Religion is put down, and the other ſet up again, then that i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> accounted Hereſie which accounted the other ſo before; ſo tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> one putting down another (in caſe they do not joyn) they ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> called Hereticks and Schiſmaticks; And ſo all Chriſtendom are or have been Schiſmaticks or Hereticks, one time or other; bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> this has not been Life. Therefore it is our deſire, that men may all come to the Light and Grace of the Spirit of God, that is gi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ven, whereby they may come to this his Royal Law, and Roya<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Society, and Natural Affections; for the others have been with out Natural Affections, who have perſecuted, impriſoned, and pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to death people, for not conforming to the Wayes, Religions an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Worſhips which they have made and ſet up with their hands, and ſuch, I ſay, have not had Natural Affections, all being mad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of one Mould, and of one Blood upon the Face of the whole Earth and that by one God, who is in all, through all, and above al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> who hath given you his Royal Law, but that you caſt it behin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:44859:20"/>your backs, <hi>Jew</hi> like; and yet made a Profeſſion of Chriſt, his Prophets and Apoſtles words; but that Profeſſion is no Profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that Religion and Worſhip is worth nothing, in that they caſt the Royal Law of God behind their backs, which teacheth you, <hi>To love your Neighbours at your ſelves,</hi> and <hi>to do to all men as you would have them do to you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now all you <hi>Chriſtians</hi> (ſo called) in <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> and elſe-where, Do not your Religions, Worſhips and Fellowſhips ſtand in outward things? yea, in ſuch things as the Kingdom of God ſtands not in: For as the Kingdom of Heaven ſtands not in <hi>Meats,</hi> nor <hi>Drinks,</hi> nor <hi>Images,</hi> nor <hi>outward Croſſes,</hi> nor <hi>Beads,</hi> nor <hi>Bells,</hi> nor <hi>Candles,</hi> nor your <hi>Maſſes</hi> you make, nor your <hi>Holy-days</hi> which you make holy, and call them <hi>holy;</hi> nor in your <hi>Steeple-Houſes,</hi> and <hi>old Maſs-Houſes,</hi> called by you <hi>Churches and Temples;</hi> Neither does the Kingdom of God ſtand in your <hi>Pictures, nor Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks of, &amp;c. nor Tippits, nor Hoods, nor Surſingle, nor White Coat, nor Black Coat, nor Altars, nor Organs, nor Surplices, Lawn-Sleeves, Coapes, Corner-Caps;</hi> nor doth it ſtand in your <hi>Sacraments of Bread and Wine,</hi> which ſome take ſtanding, ſome kneeling, ſome litting; ſome ſay, it is Chriſt's real Body and Blood no more then it ſtands in outward <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Offerings: and ſo do perſecute one another about theſe things which be meerly outward, the Inventions of your own Brain and Hands, ſince you have apoſtatized and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vened from the Spirit, ſince the Apoſtles dayes; And thus you fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low your own Traditions, and compel others to follow them, and ſo neglect the Commands of God, and of Chriſt Jeſus, who ſaid, <hi>Seek firſt the Kingdom of Heaven, and the Righteouſneſs thereof; and then in the Righteouſneſs there is Peace one with another, and with Chriſt,</hi> who is our Righteouſneſs. And ſo give over Envying, Hatred, and Perſecution, and Impriſoning, Murdering and Killing one another about theſe outward things, which the Kingdom of God ſtands not in: for it ſtands in <hi>Righteouſneſs, Faith, and in Love, and Joy in the Holy Ghoſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And come all of you to the Light of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> that you have hated, and to the Spirit of God in you, that you have vexed, grieved and quenched, and the Grace of God, that you have walkt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpightfully againſt, and turn'd unto Wantonneſs; that by it you may come to ſee your Salvation, and ceaſe from Evil, and learn
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:44859:20"/>to do well, from the Evil (I ſay) that you have done in times paſt, and do not do ſo any more for the time to come; but as God has given his Spirit to profit withal, obey it, that ſo you may profi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in Truth and Righteouſneſs, and the Love of God, that edifieth the Body, and which Love fulfils the Law, the <hi>Royal Law,</hi> which is, <hi>To do unto all as you would have all do unto you;</hi> then you will come to a holy Society, a good, righteous and juſt Society; and then you will have your equal weight and meaſure to weigh and meaſure withal: for ſuch as tranſgreſs the Royal Law of God, did and do unto others as they would not have others do unto them; and upon ſuch the <hi>Royal Law of God</hi> takes hold, and judges them; yea, upon all <hi>Jews, Chriſtians, Turks</hi> and <hi>Heathens;</hi> it doth not take notice of their Profeſſion, nor reſpect them for their Profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; but it reſpects them if <hi>they love their Neighbours as themſelves, and do unto all men as they would have all men do unto them:</hi> then it ſhews, that they have a Profeſſion of Righteouſneſs that is good, &amp; that which is juſt and holy, which is the Law of Liberty, which gives another Liberty, if he would have Liberty himſelf in this Royal Law, which is anſwered by the Spirit in every man, and the <hi>Royal Law</hi> anſwereth it.</p>
            <p>And this <hi>Royal Law</hi> takes hold upon all Men and Women in the whole Earth, let their Profeſſion be what it will be, if they grieve the Spirit of God; it judges all that walk not according to the Spirit of God in them, that brings them to the Royal Law, in which they have Liberty; and then they come to confeſs the one <hi>Legiſtator,</hi> or Law-Giver, one Lord Jeſus Chriſt, by whom is all, and one Lord, who is over all.</p>
            <p>So then let this be read ſeriouſly with the Spirit of God, in every Male and Female, that they may anſwer the <hi>Royal Law</hi> of God, in which they may all have Liberty, Unity, Commerce, Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip and a Society, a holy, a juſt, a righteous one, in which <hi>all do to others as they would have them do to them;</hi> and they come to <hi>love their Neighbours as themſelves.</hi> And in this all Nations of men may keep a Society, a Unity, a Trade, a Traffick, and a Communion, and Commerce, and hold a Correſpondency one with another; and this will preſerve him in a natural Affection: And as they all keep in this Royal Law, that anſwers the Spirit of God in them all, and his Light and Grace, in which they will have a Unity,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:44859:21"/>and by it to be kept above all the Religions and Worſhips they have made with that peeviſh ſpirit that hath led to diſobey the Spirit of God, from which they have not natural Affections, who cannot do to others as they would have others do to them, that cannot bring you to the Royal Law of God: This Royal Law will ſlay that peeviſh ſpirit in you all; and that being ſlain and fallen, then falls all Religions that you have ſet up together in the whole World. And the Spirit of the Lord turns you to the Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Law, whereof God is the Donor, and judges them that tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs it: And ſo in this Royal Law you keep dominion, and you keep your Love to your Neighbours, as to your ſelves; and the Royal Law keeps you in that Spirit, <hi>To do unto all as you would have all do unto you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>If any man</hi> (Jam. 1.23.) <hi>heareth the Word, and declareth not the ſame by his Works, he is like unto a man, beholding his natural Face in a Glaſs; for as ſoon as he looks on himſelf he goes his way, and forgets im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately what faſhion he was of: But who ſo looks into the perfect Law of Liberty, and continues therein; if he be not a forgetful Hearer, but a Doer of the Work, this man ſhall be bleſt in his Deed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now conſider this all ye that profeſs God and Chriſt, you <hi>Chriſtians, Jews,</hi> and others; for, is not this your Condition? Have you lookt into the perfect Law of Liberty? and if ſo, With what have you lookt into it? Is it not by the Spirit of God, and the Light of Chriſt? which when you have lookt into by the Spirit and Light of Chriſt Jeſus, and not done the ſame, you may read your ſelves, as in a Glaſs that you look into, and after for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get what manner of men you are.</p>
            <p>And ſo are not all that look into this perfect Law of Liberty, whether they be <hi>Jew, Chriſtian,</hi> or <hi>Heathen,</hi> who look into this perfect Law of Liberty, and doth it not, are like unto the natural Man or Woman; that look into a Glaſs, and after that, forget what manner of Men and Women they are of: and ſo they that look into the perfect Law of Liberty, and do it not, are not bleſt, nor happy in their Deeds; though they may be Hearers of this perfect Law of Liberty, and yet not Doers, they are like (I ſay) unto the Natural Man and Woman, that looks (as ſaith the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle) into the Glaſs, and after know not what manner of Men or Women they are, though they ſee themſelves when they look into
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:44859:21"/>the Glaſs. But they that look into the perfect Law of Liberty, and do the ſame, do not forget what manner of men they are, but ſee what manner of men they are, and what manner of men they have been. And ſo by the perfect Law of Liberty, looking into it, and doing it, they mend; ſo that they who have been without Natural Affections, it brings them to Natural Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; who have not loved their Nighbours as themſelves, it brings them to love them as themſelves; who have not done to all men as they would have all men do to them, this perfect Law of Liberty, looking into it, and doing of it, will bring them to do unto all as they would have all do unto them.</p>
            <p>So look upon all <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> and all that profeſs God and Chriſt in the whole World, and thoſe alſo that do not, who do grieve, and quench and vex the Spirit of God, and hate the Light of Chriſt, and walk deſpightfully againſt the Spirit of Grace, though theſe have the <hi>Word</hi> of <hi>God</hi> ſown upon all their Grounds; and if they hear it, and declare it not in their Works, Lives and Converſations, they are like a natural man beholding his Face in a Glaſs, and forgetting what manner of man he was.</p>
            <p>Then they, as was ſaid before, that do look into the Law of Liberty, and do the Law of Liberty, do know what manner of men they are, and have been, and what manner of Works, and what manner of Converſations they have been of: And ſo as the Word is ſown upon all Grounds, for all to hear it, to wit, the Stony Ground, the High-way Ground, the Thorny Ground, and the Good Heart; and though all theſe hear the Word, and do it not, they are all deceivers of their own Souls, though they may cry out againſt Deceivers without them.</p>
            <p>All Sects and People in <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> among <hi>Jews, Turks, Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens</hi> and <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> upon whoſe Ground the Word of the Lord is fown, if it be the High-way, or the Stony, or Thorny, or Good Ground; now they all hearing of this Word, and not doing it, though they may cry out againſt Deceivers without them, yet they are all Deceivers of their own Souls themſelves: For, who ſo hear the Word, hears that that puts a difference between the Precious and the Vile Words and Thoughts, Deeds and Actions: And 'tis this Word that muſt Sanctifie and Reconcile them to God, and hammers, and cuts, and hews down that that hath made a Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:44859:22"/>between them and God. And ſo they that will not hear nor regard God's Law, which is Royal and Perfect, called, <hi>The Law of Liberty,</hi> wherein the <hi>Royal Society</hi> is preſerved, and the <hi>Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Communion,</hi> and the <hi>Royal Commerce,</hi> and <hi>Natural Affections,</hi> and <hi>love their Neighbours as themſelves, and do unto all others as they would have them do unto them:</hi> And this <hi>Royal Law</hi> is from God, and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth over all Tranſgreſſors, and anſwers that which hath tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſt in all Mankind, which man muſt come to, if he comes to this <hi>Law,</hi> and comes to acknowledge, <hi>There is one Law-giver.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now there is ſomething of God in the <hi>Heathens, Turks</hi> and <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles,</hi> that when you called <hi>Chriſtians</hi> do them any Injury, they are ſenſible of the Evil, and may ſay unto you, <hi>You would not be dealt ſo with your ſelves:</hi> And the <hi>Heathen, Turks</hi> and <hi>Indians,</hi> if they do at any time that which is bad to one another, there is that in them tells them, <hi>They ſhould not have done ſo and ſo;</hi> which manifeſts ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of the Royal Law in them, which if ſeriouſly and diligently minded, would bring them <hi>To do that unto others, as they would have them do unto them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo all you called <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> or that go under that Name, Do you begin firſt <hi>to do unto others as you would have others do unto you;</hi> and ſo <hi>do you all unto the</hi> Heathen, Turks, Jews <hi>and</hi> Indians, <hi>as you would have them do unto you;</hi> ſeeing there is ſomething of God in all, that anſwers in meaſure his <hi>Royal Law,</hi> viz. <hi>To do unto all as you would have them do unto you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now all Mankind, that is, all Men and Women upon the Face of the Earth, being made of one Blood and Mould, being the Sons of <hi>Adam</hi> by nature, and all Children of God by Creation; <hi>and the Earth is the Lord's, and the Fulneſs thereof, which he hath given unto Men and Women, who dwell upon the Face of his Earth;</hi> and ſo all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Lord's Workmanſhip and Creating, he is the Law-Giver which is, <hi>to do unto all as they would have all do unto them:</hi> and God, who hath given them this juſt, good, and holy Law to all Mankind, hath placed ſomething in Man and Woman to anſwer this Law, which if they obey, then they come to <hi>do the Royal Law of God,</hi> &amp; all confeſs the <hi>one Law-giver,</hi> who is the Lord, <hi>and to love God:</hi> all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of men come to confeſs, <hi>That the Lord is the Law-giver;</hi> which Law is, <hi>To do unto all as they would have all do unto them;</hi> for if they do not, they diſobey the Principle of God in them, in the firſt
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:44859:22"/>place; and then tranſgreſs his Law, and loſe the true Weight and Meaſure, whereby they come ſhort of their Duty, <hi>In not doing unto others as they would have others do to them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now all Magiſtrates and Princes in the whole World amongſt men ſhould ſee to it, that this Law be carefully and diligently ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved and kept; namely, <hi>To do unto others as they would have others do unto them:</hi> then a royal, juſt, good and holy Society with all mankind among the ſeveral Nations in the world might be preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved: and this would keep people out of the many other Incumbran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of National Laws, whereof few know the end of, no not them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. For this <hi>Royal Law</hi> reſpects no mans Perſon, and is free, and is to be obeyed, and doth freely, and keeps freely; and in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beying and doing of it God is honoured in every heart, the Juſt and Holy God, by his juſt and holy Principle in man and woman, which brings them to do his juſt and holy Law; and by this, out of every mouth, from the Principle of God within, will the Lord be confeſt to be the Law-giver, <hi>one Law-giver</hi> and <hi>one Law, To do unto all as they would have all do unto them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now weigh the thing ſeriouſly, That ſhould all, or did all obey this <hi>Royal Law,</hi> it would be a ſpecial means to prevent a great deal of Violence, Corruptions and Cruelties now exerciſed amongſt the Children of men, as alſo that that breeds theſe Corruptions and Cruelties, it will put a check and ſtop to them, by obeying (I ſay) of it. And ſhould all people in the Univerſe obey the <hi>roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Law of God,</hi> according to the Principle of God in them, they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing encourag'd all to this, and taught all by this, it will bring them off of thoſe Debaucheries, Adulteries, Fornications, Thefts, Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, &amp;c. which ſo rage in the whole World; for <hi>the Royal Law of God,</hi> nor yet <hi>the Principle of God within,</hi> admits of no ſuch thing. And alſo this <hi>Royal Law of God,</hi> according to the Principle of God in every man, will bring all people in all their Merchandize, in buying, ſelling, and in their Husbandry, Trading and Shop-keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>To do unto all as they would have all do unto them:</hi> now in ſo do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, they honour the Lord in their Lives and Converſations, in fulfilling (I ſay) this his Royal Law.</p>
            <p>But now, as long as the Prieſts or Teachers (who are like the Framers of Religions for the diverſity and ſeveral ſorts of people in the World) do ſpeak againſt this Principle of God in every
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:44859:23"/>man, and ſay, <hi>That every man hath not a Principle of God in him, to bring him to do his Royal Law;</hi> they teach thereby the people, as well as themſelves to tranſgreſs this <hi>Royal Law, To do unto others that they would not have others do to them,</hi> as hath been ſufficiently made mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt. And therefore thoſe Teachers, who do frame Religions for people in all Nations under the whole Heaven (for they have their Religions, and their Prieſts, as well as Chriſtians, who frame Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions, as the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> Prieſts do for their people) yet theſe Teachers ſay, That every man had not ſomething of God in him, nor of his Spirit. And ſo theſe Teachers in the whole world do bring their people to thoſe Religions that they have made; and do get the Magiſtrates Power and Sword to hold then up, and allow them a Maintenance for their Preaching of it to them: And ſo hereby is begotten a great deal of Peeviſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Fury and Rage one againſt another, and one Religion maker againſt another Religion-maker, as may eaſily be ſeen over all the world; the National Religions differing one from another, and yet the people are bound to obſerve all that which their Prieſts have framed: whereas if all men and women came to the Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God in themſelves, by which they might come to the <hi>Royal Law of God;</hi> namely, <hi>In doing to others as, &amp;c.</hi> then all theſe peeviſh religions, and the Makers and Upholders of them, would quickly fall, wherein <hi>they did unto others as they would not have others do unto them.</hi> And this would be Religion, <hi>to do the Law of God,</hi> which is, <hi>To love thy Neighbour as thy ſelf, and God above all;</hi> &amp; then thou wouldſt be ready to entertain Strangers: <hi>For if thou ſhouldſt be a Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, thou wouldſt think it hard, ſhouldſt thou not be entertain'd and reliev'd;</hi> the Sick, and the Widdow and Fatherleſs <hi>the ſame compaſſion as thou wouldſt have done to thy ſelf,</hi> being in the like condition, capacity &amp; neceſſity. And this Principle of God within, in keeping the <hi>Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Law,</hi> keeps up the mind to God, <hi>who is the Law-giver,</hi> who is bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed forever, from whom they receive their Religion. And this <hi>Royal Law of God</hi> being kept by all the Sons and Daughters of men in the whole World, which is according to the Principle of God in them all, and one with it: this preſerves natural Affections, and ſo Nature in its courſe, where Nature may not be deſtroyed; for where Nature is deſtroyed, <hi>it is but by the Tranſgreſſor of the Royal Law;</hi> whereas this <hi>Royal Law</hi> being duely kept, it preſerves (I ſay)
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:44859:23"/>the <hi>Creation of God</hi> (part of which are men &amp; women) in order &amp; government themſelves, and to walk and to do to all as they, &amp;c. And out of this <hi>Royal Law of God</hi> all the Diſorder is, and all the Ill-government in the whole Creation, by diſobeying and tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing (I ſay) this <hi>Royal Law of God;</hi> yea, and all the unequal meaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Weights and falſe Judgments that are among them that do tranſgreſs and diſobey this Royal Law, which is, <hi>To do to all &amp;c.</hi> yea, and all the Ill-neighbourhood in the whole World is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them who diſobey this <hi>Royal Law of God,</hi> and quench the Spirit of the Lord in themſelves, which would lead them to obey it: And all the good Neighbourhood in the whole Univerſe is, by obeying the Principle of God in them to do the <hi>Royal Law of God,</hi> whereby they love <hi>God above all, and their Neighbour as themſelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in <hi>Ezek.</hi> 5. where the Lord ſaid, <hi>That the</hi> Jews <hi>had deſpiſed his Judgments and his Laws more then the</hi> Gentiles, <hi>and had broken his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments more then the Nations.</hi> Now mark, May not this be apply'd unto <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> who have broken and deſpiſed the Law of Life, the Law of Love, and the Law of Faith, and the Commands of Chriſt, who ſaith, <hi>Love one another, and love Enemies?</hi> Have not (I ſay) Chriſtians broken this more then the Gentile Nations and Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens? yea, we can ſay, <hi>we have found it ſo;</hi> for they are more rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to entertain Strangers then <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> who have caſt away that Command; nay, many of them are more <hi>Chriſtian</hi> in their Deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings then ſuch as are called <hi>Chriſtians;</hi> which ſignifies, that there is ſomething of God in theſe <hi>Heathens</hi> and <hi>Nations,</hi> that brings them to a ſenſibility of the Law of God, which is, <hi>To do unto all, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 117. Where <hi>David</hi> ſaith, <hi>Praiſe the Lord all ye Heathen:</hi> Which imports as much, that there is ſomething of God in the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>Heathen;</hi> elſe it would be a vain word to bid them praiſe the Lord. And again, ſaith the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> there following, <hi>Praiſe the Lord all ye Nations, &amp;c.</hi> He doth not ſay, <hi>one Nation,</hi> but all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions muſt do it. Now mark, This likewiſe imports th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> there is ſomething of God in them all, whereby they may praiſe him; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to that of the Apoſtle, who ſaith, <hi>That which is to be known of God is manifeſt in them:</hi> This he ſpeaks to the <hi>Romans,</hi> who were ſometime <hi>Heathen.</hi> So if the Prieſts Doctrine be received, who ſay, <hi>There is not ſomething of God in all Nations of men, and in the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then;</hi> then by their Doctrine (I ſay) <hi>David</hi>'s words are needleſs,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:44859:24"/>who exhorts <hi>all Nations and Heathens to praiſe the Lord:</hi> But <hi>David</hi> full well knew what he ſpoke, who ſaw Chriſt; but the Prieſts ſee not themſelves, and ſo are Judges in their evil Thoughts of the Scripture and holy Mens words, whoſe judgment is judged by the holy men's words.</p>
            <p>Pſal. 100. <hi>Be joyful in the Lord all ye Lands, and ſerve the Lord with Gladneſs, and come before his Preſence with a Song: be ye ſure that the Lord is God; he it is that made us, not we our ſelves.</hi> Now mark this general Doctrine of <hi>David</hi>'s, who would have <hi>all the Lands to be joyful in the Lord, &amp;c.</hi> Here <hi>David</hi> made no Sect, as if ſome people only were to ſerve him, and as if ſome people only were to praiſe him; no ſaith he, <hi>All Nations and all Heathen are to praiſe the Lord:</hi> And now, if they all ſerve the Lord, and praiſe him, then they all obey his Law, his <hi>Royal Law,</hi> which is, <hi>To do to all as they would have all do to them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Iſa. 51. <hi>The Iſlands of the</hi> Gentiles <hi>ſhall hope in me, and put their truſt in my Arm.</hi> Here you ſee is a Promiſe made unto the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, that they ſhould truſt in the Arm of the Lord, and hope in God; which clearly implies, <hi>that there is ſomething of God in them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in <hi>Rom.</hi> 15. where the Apoſtle writes to thoſe that were ſometime Heathens, how that <hi>the Offering of the Gentile ſhould be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted of God;</hi> now this was a ſpiritual Sacrifice: and how <hi>the Lord would be praiſed among the Gentiles, and he ſhould be lauded among all the Nations; and praiſe him</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>among all the Nations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And again, the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſaith, <hi>There ſhall be a Root of</hi> Jeſſe, &amp; <hi>he ſhall ariſe to reign over the</hi> Gentiles, <hi>in him ſhall the</hi> Gentiles <hi>truſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that 'tis undoubtedly clear here, that there is ſomething of God in all the Gentiles, in all the Nations and People, which would praiſe the Lord; and by that of God in them they come to know the Root of <hi>Jeſſe,</hi> viz. <hi>Chriſt Jeſus to reign over them;</hi> who is the Light, and enlighteneth them, they ſee him, by which Light Chriſt hath enlightened them withal; all ſuch truſt in Chriſt, who reigns over them, and rules over them: and ſo they come to do his Law and Commandments, his Royal Law of Love, of Life, and of Faith, by which they come <hi>to do unto all as they would have all do unto them, and to love their Neighbours as themſelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>George Fox.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:44859:24"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
